Cities are like siblings in a large polygamous family.
المدن كالأشقاء فى عائلة كبيرة متعددة الزوجات.
Each one has a unique personality and is headed in a distinct direction.
كل فرد لدية شخصية فريدة موجهةً لاتجاه معين.
But they all have somewhat shared origins.
ولكن لديهم جميعاً أصول مشتركة إلى حد ما.
Sometimes I think postcolonial cities are like the children
أحيانا أعتقد أن المدن بعد الاستعمار تشبة الأطفال
of the two least-favorite wives,
من الزوجتين الأقل تفضيلاً،
who are constantly being asked,
الذين يُطالبون باستمرار،
"Ah, why can't you be more like your sister?"
"آه، لماذا لا يمكنكي أن تكوني مثل أختك؟"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
The "why" of cities is largely the same, no matter where they are:
و "لماذا" تلك للمدن هي نفسها إلى حد كبير، بغض النظر عن مكان وجود المدن:
an advantageous location that makes trade and administration possible;
الموقع المتميز الذى يجعل التجارة والإدارة ممكنة؛
the potential for scalable opportunities
القدرة على توفير الفرص القابلة للتطوير
for the skilled and unskilled alike;
للماهر وغير الماهر على حد سواء؛
a popular willingness to be in constant flux
والرغبة الشعبية في أن تستمر في التدفق
and, of course, resilience.
وبالطبع، القدرة على الصمود.
The "how" of cities, however, is a whole other story.
لكن "كيف" للمدن، هي قصة أخرى كاملة.
How are they run?
كيف تُدار؟
How do they grow?
كيف تنمو؟
How do they decide who belongs and who doesn't?
كيف يقررون من ينتمى ومن لا ينتمى؟
Lagos is my home.
لاغوس هى موطني.
You can always find the Nigerians
تستطيع دائما أن تجد النيجريين
by following the noise and the dancing, right?
باتباع الضوضاء والرقص، أليس كذلك؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Like any major city, that place is a lot of things,
مثل أى مدينة رئيسية، هذا المكان عبارة عن أشياء كثيرة،
many of which are highly contradictory.
الكثير منها متناقضة للغاية،
Our public transportation doesn't quite work,
مواصلاتنا العامة لا تعمل إلى حد كبير،
so we have these privately owned bright yellow buses
لذلك لدينا هذه الحافلات الصفراء اللامعة المملوكة للقطاع الخاص
that regularly cause accidents.
التى تتسبب بحوادث بشكل منتظم.
Luxury car showrooms line badly maintained and often flooded roads.
خط معارض السيارات الباهظة تتم صيانتها بشكل سيء وغالبا ما تغطي الطرق،
Street evangelism is only slightly less ubiquitous
عمليات التبشير في الشارع توجد بشكل أقل بقليل
than street harassment.
من التحرش من الشوارع.
Sex workers sometimes have two degrees, a bank job
العاملات فى مجال الجنس أحيانا يكون لديهن درجتين جامعيتين، ووظيفة بنكية
and a prominent role in church.
ودور بارز فى الكنيسة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
On any given day,
فى أي يوم من الأيام،
there can be either a party or a burned body
يمكن أن يكون هناك حفلة أو جسد محترق
in the middle of a street.
في منتصف الطريق.
There is so much that is possible in Lagos
هناك الكثير مما هو محتمل في لاغوس
and so much that isn't,
والكثير مما هو غير محتمل،
and very often the difference between possibility and impossibility
وغالبا الاختلاف بين الإمكانية والإستحالة
is simply who you are,
يكون ببساطة من تكون،
and if you're lucky enough, who you're connected to.
وإذا كنت محظوظًا بما فيه الكفاية، من الذين تتصل بهم.
Belonging in Lagos is a fluid concept
الانتماء للاغوس مفهوم لا محدود
determined by ethnic origin, sexual orientation, gender,
يتحدد بالأصل العرقي، والتوجة الجنسي، والنوع
but most visibly and often most violently,
ولكن أكثر وضوحاً وغالباً أكثر عنفاً،
class.
هو الفئة.
Before Nigeria became a country,
قبل أن تصبح نيجيريا دولة،
fisherpeople from the inland creeks started to come down the Lagos lagoon
بدء الصيادون من الجداول المائية النزول إلى بحيرة لاغوس
and establish villages along the coast.
وأنشأوا القرى على طول الساحل.
About 60 years later, my grandfather, Oludotun Adekunle Kukoyi,
بعد حوالي ستون سنة، جدي، أولودوتن أديكونل كوكوي،
also arrived in Lagos.
أيضاً وصل إلى لاغوس.
Like me, he was an alumnus of the University of Ibadan,
شأنه شأني، كان طالباً في جامعة إيبادان،
a young member of the educated elite in the independence era.
وهو عضو شاب من النخبة المتعلمة في عهد الإستقلال.
Over time, he built an illustrious career as a land surveyor,
مع الوقت، بنى حياة مهنية لامعة كمساح للأراضي،
mapping out now-bustling neighborhoods
ورسم خرائط للأحياء الصاخبة الآن
when they were just waist-high wild grass.
عندما كانوا مجرد أعشاب عالية متوسطة.
He died when I was nine.
لقد توفي عندما كنت فى التاسعة.
And by that time, my family, like the families of those fisherpeople,
ومنذ ذلك الوقت، عائلتى مثل كل عائلات الصيادين أولئك،
knew Lagos as home.
عرفت لاغوس بالوطن.
Among the Yoruba, we have a saying,
بين اليوروبا، لدينا قول،
"Èkó gb’olè, ó gb’ọ̀lẹ,"
"لاغوس هي الأرض"
which can be translated to mean that Lagos will welcome anyone.
والتى يمكن أن يترجم ليعني أن لاغوس سترحب بأي شخص.
But that saying is becoming less and less true.
ولكن هذا القول يصبح أقل وأقل صحة.
Many Lagosians, including the descendants of those fisherpeople
العديد من أهل لاغوس، ومنهم أحفاد الصيادين أولئك
who arrived generations before my grandfather,
الذين وصلوا قبل جدي بأجيال،
are now being pushed out
قد دُفعوا الآن للخارج
to make room for an emergent city
لإفساح المجال من أجل إنشاء مدينة
that has been described as "the new Dubai."
التي تم وصفها بأنها "دبى الجديدة."
You see, Lagos inspires big dreams, even in its leaders,
أنتم ترون، لاغوس تخلق أحلام كبيرة، حتى عند قادتها،
and successive governments have declared aspirations
وحكوماتها المتتالية قد أعلنت طموحاتها
towards a megacity where poverty does not exist.
تجاة مدنٍ ضخمةٍ حيث لا يوجد فقر فيها.
Unfortunately, instead of focusing on the eradication of poverty
لسوء الحظ، بدلا من التركيز على استئصال الفقر
as you would expect,
كما تتوقعون،
the strategy of choice focuses on eliminating the poor.
تركز استراتيجية الاختيار على القضاء على الفقراء.
Last October, the Governor announced plans
فى إكتوبر الماضي، أعلن المحافظ خطط
to demolish every single waterfront settlement in Lagos.
لهدم كل واجهة بحرية فردية موجودة في (لاغوس).
There are more than 40 of these indigenous communities
هناك أكثر من أربعين من هذه المجتمعات الأصلية
all over the city,
في جميع أنحاء المدينة،
with over 300,000 people living in them.
وبها حوالى ثلاثمائة ألف نسمة يعيشون بها.
Otodo Gbame,
أوتودوغبامي،
a hundred-year-old fishing village
قرية صيد عمرها مائة عام
with a population about three-quarters that of Monaco
وتعداد سكانها يمثل حوالى ثلاثة أرباع السكان في موناكو
and similar potential for beachfront luxury --
وإمكانات مماثلة للشاطئ الفاخر...
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
was one of the first to be targeted.
فكانت واحدة من أول المستهدفين.
I first heard of Otodo Gbame after the demolition started.
لقد سمعت أول مرة عن أوتودوغبامي بعد ما بدء الهدم.
When I visited in November 2016, I met Magdalene Aiyefoju.
عندما زرتها فى نوفمبر عام 2016 التقيت ماجدالينا أييفوجو.
She is a now-homeless woman
وهي الآن امرأة متشردة
whose surname means, "the world is blind."
ولقبها يعني، "العالم أعمى."
Magdalene's son Basil was one of over 20 people
باسل ابن ماجدالينا كان واحداً من أكثر من عشرين شخصاً
who were shot, drowned
من الذين قُتِلوا، غُرِقوا
or presumed dead in that land grab.
أو ماتوا اثناء الإستيلاء على الأراضي.
Standing outside her shelter, I saw the two white-sand football fields
واقفة خارج ملجئها، رأيت ملعبي كرة القدم ذات الرمال البيضاء
where Basil used to play.
حيث اعتاد أن يلعب باسل.
Spread all around us were the ruins of schools, churches,
كان ينتشر من حولنا أنقاض المدارس، والكنائس،
a primary health center, shops,
ومركز صحي رئيسي، ومحلات تجارية،
thousands of homes.
والآلاف من المنازل.
Young children enthusiastically helped to put up shelters,
الأطفال الصغار يساعدون بحماس في بناء الملاجىء،
and about 5,000 of the residents, with nowhere else to go,
وحوالى خمسة ألآف ساكن ، بدون أي مكان آخر يذهبون إليه،
simply stayed put.
ببساطة بقي هذا الوضع.
And then in April,
ثم في أبريل،
state security personnel came back.
عاد أفراد أمن الدولة.
This time, they cleared the community out completely,
في هذا الوقت، طهروا المجتمع تماما،
with beatings, bullets and fire.
بالقتل، والرصاص، والنار.
As I speak, there are construction crews preparing Otodo Gbame's beaches
وأنا أتحدث، هناك طواقم بناء لإعداد شواطىء أوتودوغبامي
for anyone who can afford a multi-million-dollar view.
من أجل أي شخص قادر على تحمل عرض بملايين الدولارات.
The new development is called "Periwinkle Estate."
التطوير الجديد يدعى "بريوينكل إستات."
Forced evictions are incredibly violent and, of course, unconstitutional.
عمليات الإخلاء القسري عنيفة بشكل لا يصدق وبطبيعة الحال، غير دستورية
And yet, they happen so often in so many of our cities,
ومع ذلك، فإنها تحدث في كثير من الأحيان في الكثير من مدننا،
because the first thing we are taught to forget about poor people
لأن أول شيء نتعلم غض الطرف عنه بالنسبة للفقراء
is that they are people.
ننسى أنهم بشر.
We believe that a home is a thing a person absolutely has a right to,
نحن نؤمن أن البيت هو شيء للشخص الحق المطلق فيه،
unless the person is poor and the home is built a certain way
إلا إذا كان الشخص فقيراً وقد تم بناء المنزل بطريقة معينة
in a certain neighborhood.
وفي حي معين.
But there is no single definition of the word "home."
ولكن ليس هناك تعريف واحد لكلمة "المنزل."
After all, what is a slum besides an organic response
بعد كل ذلك، ماذا تكون الأحياء الفقيرة إلى جانب الاستجابة العضوية
to acute housing deficits and income inequality?
للعجز الحاد في المساكن وعدم المساواة في الدخل؟
And what is a shanty if not a person making a home for themselves
وما هو المأوى إذا لم يكن الأشخاص يصنعون المنزل من أجل أنفسهم
against all odds?
ضد كل الصعوبات؟
Slums are an imperfect housing solution,
الأحياء الفقيرة هي حل غير متكامل للإسكان،
but they are also prime examples of the innovation, adaptability
ولكنها أيضا نماذج أولية من أجل الابتكار والتكيف
and resilience at the foundation --
والقدرة على الصمود في المؤسسة ...
and the heart --
والقلب...
of every functional city.
لكل مدينة عملية.
You don't need to be the new Dubai
أنت لا تحتاج أن تكون دبي الجديدة
when you're already Lagos.
عندما تكون بالفعل لاغوس.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
We have our own identity,
لدينا هويتنا الخاصة،
our own rhythm,
تناغمنا الخاص،
and as anyone who knows Lagos can tell you,
ومثل أي شخص يعرف لاغوس يمكنه أن يخبرك،
poor Lagosians are very often the source of the city's character.
بأن أهل لاغوس الفقراء غالبا ما يمثلون المصدر الرئيسي لطابع المدينة.
Without its poor, Lagos would not be known for its music
لولا فقرائها، لما عُرِفت لاغوس بموسيقاها
or its endless energy
أو طاقتها التي لا نهاية لها
or even the fact that you can buy an ice cold drink or a puppy
أو حتى الحقيقة أنك تستطيع شراء مشروب بارد أو جرو
through your car window.
من خلال شباك سيارتك.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
The conditions that cause us to define certain neighborhoods as slums
الظروف التي تجعلنا نحدد أحياء معينة بأنها أحياء فقيرة
can be effectively improved,
يمكن تحسينها تحسيناً فعالاً،
but not without recognizing the humanity and the agency
ولكن ليس دون الاعتراف بإنسانية وقوة
of the people living in them.
الناس الذين يعيشون بها.
In Lagos, where public goods are rarely publicly available,
في لاغوس، حيث السلع العامة نادراً ما تكون متاحة للجمهور،
slum dwellers are often at the forefront of innovating solutions.
سكان الأحياء الفقيرة غالباً ما يكونوا في طليعة الحلول المبتكرة.
After being disconnected from the grid for months
بعد قطع الاتصال بشبكة الكهرباء لعدة أشهر
because the power company couldn't figure out how to collect bills,
لأن شركة الطاقة لا تستطيع معرفة كيفية جمع الفواتير،
one settlement designed a system that collectivized remittances
صممت واحدة من المستوطنات نظام يجمع التحويلات المالية
and got everyone cheaper rates into the bargain.
وحصل الجميع على أسعار أرخص في الصفقة.
Another settlement created a reform program
مستوطنة أخرى أنشأت برنامج إصلاحي
that hires local bad boys as security.
التي تستأجر الأولاد السيئين المحليين كأمن.
They know every trick and every hideout,
إنهم يعرفون كل خدعة وكل مخبأ،
so now troublemakers are more likely to get caught and reported to police
حتى الآن مثيري الشغب هم الأكثر عرضة للإعتقال وإبلاغ الشرطة عنهم
and fewer of the youth end up engaging in criminal activity.
والقليل من الشباب في نهاية المطاف ينخرطون في النشاط الإجرامي.
Yet another settlement recently completed
وقد استكملت مؤخراً مستوطنة أخرى
a flood-safe, eco-friendly communal toilet system.
نظام حمامات عموميةٍ، آمنةٍ من الفيضانات وصديقةٍ للبيئة
Models like these are being adopted across Lagos.
النماذج التي مثل هذه تُعتمد في جميع أنحاء لاغوس
Informal settlements are incorrectly named as the problem.
المستوطنات العشوائية سميت بصورة غير صحيحة بأنها مشكلة.
In fact, the real problems are the factors that create them,
في الحقيقة، المشكلات الحقيقية هي العوامل التي تخلقها،
like the entrenchment of poverty,
مثل ترسخ الفقر،
social exclusion
والإقصاء الاجتماعي
and state failures.
وإخفاقات الدولة.
When our governments frame slums as threats
عندما تُعرف حكوماتنا الأحياء الفقيرة بإنها تهديدات
in order to justify violent land grabs or forced evictions,
من أجل تبرير الاستيلاء على الأراضي العنيفة أو الإخلاء القسري،
they're counting on those of us who live in formal housing
إنهم يعتمدون على هؤلاء الذين يعيشون في مساكن رسمية منا
to tacitly and ignorantly agree with them.
لكي ننضم ونتفق معهم دون علم.
Rather, we must remind them
بل، علينا أن نذكرهم
that governments exist to serve not only those who build
أن الحكومات تتواجد لخدمة ليس فقط من يبني
and live in luxury homes,
ويعيش فى منازل باهظة الثمن،
but also those who clean and guard them.
ولكن أيضاً من ينظفونها ويحرسوها.
Our --
...
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
our realities may differ,
قد تختلف حقائقنا،
but our rights don't.
ولكن لا تختلف حقوقنا.
The Lagos state government,
حكومة ولاية لاغوس،
like far too many on our continent,
مثل عدد كبير جداً فى قارتنا،
pays lip service to ideas of inclusion,
تدفع الخدمات الى أفكار التضمين،
while acting as though progress can only be achieved
بينما تتصرف كما وكأن الهدف لا يمكن تحقيقة إلا من خلال
by the erasure, exploitation and even elimination of groups
المحو، والاستغلال وحتى القضاء على الجماعات
it considers expendable.
التي تعتبرها مستهلكة.
People living with disabilities who hawk or beg on Lagos streets
الأشخاص الذين يعانون من الإعاقات الذين يتسولون أو يبيعون في شوارع لاغوس
are rounded up, extorted
يتم جمعهم، وابتزازهم
and detained.
واحتجازهم.
Women in low-income neighborhoods are picked up
النساء في الأحياء ذات الدخل المنخفض يؤخذون
and charged with prostitution,
ويتم إتهامهم بالدعارة.
regardless of what they actually do for a living.
بغض النظر عن ما يفعلنه في الواقع من أجل العيش.
Gay citizens are scapegoated to distract from real political problems.
هؤلاء المواطنين هم كبش الفداء لصرف النظر عن المشاكل السياسية الحقيقية.
But people, like cities, are resilient,
ولكن الناس، مثل المدن، يبقون صامدين،
and no amount of legislation or intimidation or violence
وليس هناك قدر من التشريعات أو التخويف أو العنف
can fully eliminate any of us.
يمكنه القضاء تماماً على أي منا.
Prostitutes, women and women who work as prostitutes
العاهرات، النساء اللواتى يعملن كعاهرات
still haven't gone extinct,
لا يزالن موجودات،
despite centuries of active suppression.
بالرغم من قرون من القمع النشط.
Queer Africans continue to exist,
لا يزال الأفارقة المتحررون موجودين،
even though queerness is now criminalized in most parts of the continent.
بالرغم من أن التحرر يجرم الآن في معظم أنحاء القارة.
And I'm fairly certain that poor people don't generally tend to just disappear
وأنا واثقة إلى حد ما أن الفقراء لا تميل عادة إلى أن تختفي فقط
because they've been stripped of everything they have.
لأنهم قد تم تجريدهم من كل ما لديهم.
We are all already here,
نحن جميعاً هنا بالفعل،
and that answers the question
وهذا يجيب على السؤال
of whether or not we belong.
ما اذا كنا ننتمى أم لا.
When those fisherpeople started to sail down the lagoon
عندما بدء هؤلاء الصيادون بالإبحار أسفل البحيرة
in search of new homes,
للبحث عن منازل جديدة،
it could not have occurred to them
لم يكن واضحاً لهم
that the city that would rise up around them
أن المدينة التي ترتفع من حولهم
would one day insist that they do not belong in it.
يوما ما ستصر على أنهم لا ينتمون إليها.
I like to believe that my grandfather,
أريد أن أصدق أن جدي،
in mapping new frontiers for Lagos,
في رسم حدود جديدة للاغوس،
was trying to open it up
كان يحاول أن ينفتح
to make room for other people to be welcomed by the city
لإفساح المجال لأشخاص آخرين ليكونوا موضع ترحيب من قبل المدينة
in the same way that he was.
بنفس الطريقة التي كان عليها.
On my way here, my grandma called me
في طريقي هنا، اتصلت بي جدتي
to remind me how proud she was,
لتذكرنى إلى أي مدى هى فخورة بي،
how proud [my grandfather] and my mother would have been.
كيف سيكون [جدي] وأمى فخورين بى.
I am their dreams come true.
أنا أمثل أحلامهم التي تتحقق.
But there is no reason why their dreams -- or mine, for that matter --
ولكن ليس هناك سبب وراء لماذا أحلامهم ... أو أحلامنا، في هذه المسالة...
are allowed to come true
سمح لها بأن تصبح حقيقة
while those of others are turned to nightmares.
فى حين أن أحلام آخرين تحولت إلى كوابيس.
And lest we forget:
ولئلا ننسى:
the minimum requirement for a dream
أن الحد الأدنى من متطلبات الحلم
is a safe place to lay your head.
هو مكان آمن لوضع رأسك.
It is too late now for Basil,
لقد فات الأوان الآن بالنسبة لباسل،
but not for Magdalene,
ولكن ليس بالنسبة لمجدالينا،
not for the hundreds of thousands,
ليس بالنسبة لمئات من الألوف،
the millions still under threat in Lagos
أو الملايين الذين ما زالوا معرضين للخطر في لاغوس
or any of our cities.
أو أي من مدننا،
The world does not have to remain blind
العالم لا يجب أن يبقى أعمى
to the suffering that is created when we deny people's humanity,
إتجاة المعاناة التى تنشأ عندما تنعدم إنسانية البشر،
or even to the incredible potential for growth that exists
أو حتى إلى الإمكانيات التي لا تصدق للنمو القائم
when we recognize and value all contributions.
عندما ندرك ونقدر جميع المساهمات.
We must hold our governments
علينا أن نحمل حكوماتنا
and ourselves
وأنفسنا
accountable
المسؤولية
for keeping our shared cities safe for everyone in them,
للحفاظ على الأمن المشترك في مدننا لكل فرد بها،
because the only cities worth building --
لأن المدن الوحيدة التي تستحق البناء...
indeed, the only futures worth dreaming of --
بل المستقبل الوحيد الذي يستحق أن نحلم به...
are those that include all of us,
هو المستقبل الذي يشملنا كلنا،
no matter who we are
بغض النظر عن من نكون
or how we make homes for ourselves.
أو كيف نصنع المنازل من أجل أنفسنا.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)